Guide to the James Braxton Craven Papers, 1961-1977 RL.00266
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
James Braxton Craven papers
1961-1977
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Craven, James Braxton
RL.00266
224 Linear Feet
North Carolina lawyer and federal judge. The legal and judicial papers of U.S. Circuit Court Judge James Braxton Craven span the years 1961-1977. Files of correspondence, memoranda, and legal motions and orders concern a multitude of cases in which Craven was involved. Cases include civil suits; criminal cases, including many prisoners' petitions for Writs of Habeas Corpus, particularly since Gideon v. Wainwright; and appeals from administrative boards and commissions, including the FCC, SEC, NLRB, and others. After 1970, Craven served on "three-judge" district court sessions, special courts which usually relate to civil suits raising questions of governmental policy and of constitutional law, and the files document these as well. There are also files dating from 1964-1973 which concern school integration cases. The correspondence between judges is particularly significant, revealing the intersection of personal belief and the carrying out of judicial processes in the lower and higher courts. The collection also includes a précis outlining the legal philosophy and the highlights of Craven's career, but contains very little personal material.
168,210 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The James Braxton Craven Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 1978.
Biographical Note
Chronology
1918 April 3 James Braxton Craven born in Lenoir County, N.C., son of a Methodist minister
1939 A.B., Duke University
1942 LL.B., Harvard University
1942-1946 Served in U.S. Navy
1946 Admitted to North Carolina Bar Solicitor of the Burke County Criminal Court
1948-1952 Assistant U.S. Attorney for the Western District of North Carolina
1956 Appointed North Carolina Superior Judge
1959-1960 Vice President of the North Carolina Bar Association
1961 Appointed Chief Judge of the U.S. District Court for the Western District in North Carolina
1963 Elected a member of the Institute of Judicial Administration
1966-1977 U.S. Circuit Judge, Fourth Circuit Court of Appeals
1967 Visiting professor in constitutional law at the University of North Carolina Law School
1968 Visiting professor in federal courts at the University of Texas Law School
1970 Visiting professor in constitutional law at the University of North Carolina Law School
1972-1973 Duke University Board of Trustees member
1977 May 3 Death of James Braxton Craven at age 59
Collection Overview
The legal and judicial papers of U.S. Circuit Court Judge James Braxton Craven span the years 1961-1977. Files of correspondence, memoranda, and legal motions and orders concern a multitude of cases in which Craven was involved. Cases include civil suits; criminal cases, including many prisoners' petitions for Writs of Habeas Corpus, particularly since Gideon v. Wainwright; and appeals from administrative boards and commissions, including the FCC, SEC, NLRB, and others. After 1970, Craven served on "three-judge" district court sessions, special courts which usually relate to civil suits raising questions of governmental policy and of constitutional law, and the files document these as well. There are also files dating from 1964-1973 which concern school integration cases. The correspondence between judges is particularly significant, revealing the intersection of personal belief and the carrying out of judicial processes in the lower and higher courts. The collection also includes a précis outlining the legal philosophy and the highlights of Craven's career, but contains very little personal material. Arrangement is in one large alphabetical file, prefaced by a file of biographical information.
Appellate courts -- United States; Appellate courts -- North Carolina; School desegregation; North Carolina -- Politics and government -- 20th century; Law -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Prisoners -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- United States; Criminal Justice Act -- United States; Federal Magistrates Act -- United States; Judges -- North Carolina; Judges -- United States -- Correspondence; Civil rights -- Education -- United States; Courts -- United States -- History; Criminal courts -- United States; Criminal justice, Administration of -- United States; United States. Court of Appeals (Fourth Circuit) -- History; Craven, James Braxton
- Alphabetical Series, 1961-1977, 267 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  The bulk of the series is taken up by many boxes of files from U.S. Court of Appeals cases. Each box contains approximately .5 linear feet of material. Other smaller sections contain files on U.S. District Court cases, files on the Criminal Justice and the Federal Magistrates acts, correspondence between judges, school civil rights cases, administrative files, and judicial conferences.
  - Biographical information; inventory of collection (Box 1)
  - Administrative Office of the U.S. Courts: Reports, 1970-1976 (Box 1)
  - Appellate Judges Seminar and Planning Committee, 1974-1976 (Box 2)
  - Appellate Justice Noational Conference, San Diego, Ca., 1975 (Box 3)
  - Clare Plan (re: standards for admission to practice in the federal courts), 1975-1977 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: "Crackpot Letters," 1962-1977 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with eleven judges, 1961-1977 (Box 5)
  - Criminal Justice Act, 1964-1966 (Box 6)
  - Federal Magistrates Act, 1969-1970 (Box 6)
  - School Civil Rights Cases, 1964-1973 (Box 7)
  - U.S. Court of Appeals, Fourth Circuit
    - Cases, 1968-1977
      Scope and Contents
      Cases 8790 to 15713 date from 1968 to 1970. Cases 71-1001 to 77-1631 date from 1971 to 1977.
      - Legal cases, 8790-10357 (Box 8)
      - Legal cases, 10358-10552 (Box 9)
      - Legal cases, 10554-10640 (Box 10)
      - Legal cases, 10641-10755 (Box 11)
      - Legal cases, 10756-10822 (Box 12)
      - Legal cases, 10823-10974 (Box 13)
      - Legal cases, 10975-11029 (Box 14)
      - Legal cases, 11030-11099 (Box 15)
      - Legal cases, 11100-11192 (Box 16)
      - Legal cases, 11193-11300 (Box 17)
      - Legal cases, 11302-11399 (Box 18)
      - Legal cases, 11404-11516 (Box 19)
      - Legal cases, 11517-11569 (Box 20)
      - Legal cases, 11570-11649 (Box 21)
      - Legal cases, 11650-11748 (Box 22)
      - Legal cases, 11750-11899 (Box 23)
      - Legal cases, 11900-12018 (Box 24)
      - Legal cases, 12019-12099 (Box 25)
      - Legal cases, 12101-12237 (Box 26)
      - Legal cases, 12240-12344 (Box 27)
      - Legal cases, 12351-12440 (Box 28)
      - Legal cases, 12441-12497 (Box 29)
      - Legal cases, 12500-12596 (Box 30)
      - Legal cases, 12600-12679 (Box 31)
      - Legal cases, 12680-12748 (Box 32)
      - Legal cases, 12752-12828 (Box 33)
      - Legal cases, 12830-12874 (Box 34)
      - Legal cases, 12875-12938 (Box 35)
      - Legal cases, 12940-13039 (Box 36)
      - Legal cases, 13040-13148 (Box 37)
      - Legal cases, 13149-13246 (Box 38)
      - Legal cases, 13247-13290 (Box 39)
      - Legal cases, 13291-13349 (Box 40)
      - Legal cases, 13350-13424 (Box 41)
      - Legal cases, 13425-13517 (Box 42)
      - Legal cases, 13518-13599 (Box 43)
      - Legal cases, 13600-13719 (Box 44)
      - Legal cases, 13720-13807 (Box 45)
      - Legal cases, 13808-13903 (Box 46)
      - Legal cases, 13904-13949 (Box 47)
      - Legal cases, 13950-14028 (Box 48)
      - Legal cases, 14029-14099 (Box 49)
      - Legal cases, 14100-14209 (Box 50)
      - Legal cases, 14210-14298 (Box 51)
      - Legal cases, 14299-14399 (Box 52)
      - Legal cases, 14400-14502 (Box 53)
      - Legal cases, 14503-14561 (Box 54)
      - Legal cases, 14562-14629 (Box 55)
      - Legal cases, 14630-14764 (Box 56)
      - Legal cases, 14765-14836 (Box 57)
      - Legal cases, 14837-14927 (Box 58)
      - Legal cases, 14928-14968 (Box 59)
      - Legal cases, 14969-15040 (Box 60)
      - Legal cases, 15041-15089 (Box 61)
      - Legal cases, 15090-15169 (Box 62)
      - Legal cases, 15170-15237 (Box 63)
      - Legal cases, 15238-15289 (Box 64)
      - Legal cases, 15290-15383 (Box 65)
      - Legal cases, 15384-15713 (Box 66)
      - Legal cases, 71-1001 - 71-1082 (Box 67)
      - Legal cases, 71-1083 - 71-1155 (Box 68)
      - Legal cases, 71-1156 - 71-1269 (Box 69)
      - Legal cases, 71-1270 - 71-1358 (Box 70)
      - Legal cases, 71-1359 - 71-1411 (Box 71)
      - Legal cases, 71-1412 - 71-1506 (Box 72)
      - Legal cases, 71-1507 - 71-1572 (Box 73)
      - Legal cases, 71-1573 - 71-1629 (Box 74)
      - Legal cases, 71-1630 - 71-1716 (Box 75)
      - Legal cases, 71-1717 - 71-71-1774 (Box 76)
      - Legal cases, 71-1775 - 71-1861 (Box 77)
      - Legal cases, 71-1862 - 71-1925 (Box 78)
      - Legal cases, 71-1926 - 71-1999 (Box 79)
      - Legal cases, 71-2000 - 71-2100 (Box 80)
      - Legal cases, 71-2101 - 71-2177 (Box 81)
      - Legal cases, 71-2178 - 71-2219 (Box 82)
      - Legal cases, 72-1001 - 72-1055 (Box 83)
      - Legal cases, 72-1056 - 72-1074 (Box 84)
      - Legal cases, 72-1075 - 72-1182 (Box 85)
      - Legal cases, 72-1183 - 72-1238 (Box 86)
      - Legal cases, 72-1239 - 72-1266 (Box 87)
      - Legal cases, 72-1267 - 72-1314 (Box 88)
      - Legal cases, 72-1315 - 72-1396 (Box 89)
      - Legal cases, 72-1397 - 72-1470 (Box 90)
      - Legal cases, 72-1471 - 72-1544 (Box 91)
      - Legal cases, 72-1545 - 72-1613 (Box 92)
      - Legal cases, 72-1614 - 72-1692 (Box 93)
      - Legal cases, 72-1693 - 72-1739 (Box 94)
      - Legal cases, 72-1740 - 72-1819 (Box 95)
      - Legal cases, 72-1820 - 72-1897 (Box 96)
      - Legal cases, 72-1898 - 72-1999 (Box 97)
      - Legal cases, 72-2000 - 72-2067 (Box 98)
      - Legal cases, 72-2068 - 72-2216 (Box 99)
      - legal cases, 72-2217 - 72-2321 (Box 100)
      - Legal cases, 72-2322 - 72-2368 (Box 101)
      - Legal cases, 72-2369 - 72-2428 (Box 102)
      - Legal cases, 72-2429 - 72-2469 (Box 103)
      - Legal cases, 72-2470 - 72-2519 (Box 104)
      - Legal cases, 73-1001 - 73-1027 (Box 105)
      - Legal cases, 73-1028 - 73-1062 (Box 106)
      - Legal cases, 73-1063 - 73-1142 (Box 107)
      - Legal cases, 73-1143 - 73-1186 (Box 108)
      - Legal cases, 73-1187 - 73-1233 (Box 109)
      - Legal cases, 73-1234 - 73-1282 (Box 110)
      - Legal cases, 73-1283 - 73-1366 (Box 111)
      - Legal cases, 73-1367 - 73-1476 (Box 112)
      - Legal cases, 73-1477 - 73-1521 (Box 113)
      - Legal cases, 73-1522 - 73-1587 (Box 114)
      - Legal cases, 73-1588 - 73-1633 (Box 115)
      - Legal cases, 73-1634 - 73-1699 (Box 116)
      - Legal cases, 73-1652 - 73-1833 (Box 117, Box 118)
      - Legal cases, 73-1700 - 73-1751 (Box 119)
      - Legal cases, 73-1752 - 73-1812 (Box 120)
      - Legal cases, 73-1813 - 73-1852 (Box 121)
      - Legal cases, 73-1853 - 73-1899 (Box 122)
      - Legal cases, 73-1900 - 73-1939 (Box 123)
      - Legal cases, 73-1940 - 73-1997 (Box 124)
      - Legal cases, 73-1998 - 73-2059 (Box 125)
      - Legal cases, 73-2060 - 73-2118 (Box 126)
      - Legal cases, 73-2119 - 73-2211 (Box 127)
      - Legal cases, 73-2212 - 73-2270 (Box 128)
      - Legal cases, 73-2271 - 73-2321 (Box 129)
      - Legal cases, 73-2322 - 73-2353 (Box 130)
      - Legal cases, 73-2354 - 73-2396 (Box 131)
      - Legal cases, 73-2397 - 73-2451 (Box 132)
      - Legal cases, 73-2452 - 73-2499 (Box 133)
      - Legal cases, 73-2500 - 73-2518 (Box 134)
      - Legal cases, 73-2519 - 73-2526 (Box 135)
      - Legal cases, 74-1003 - 74-1059 (Box 136)
      - Legal cases, 74-1060 - 74-1124 (Box 137)
      - Legal cases, 74-1125 - 74-1193 (Box 138)
      - Legal cases, 74-1194 - 74-1225 (Box 139)
      - Legal cases, 74-1226 - 74-1259 (Box 140)
      - Legal cases, 74-1260 - 74-1336 (Box 141)
      - Legal cases, 74-1337 - 74-1374 (Box 142)
      - Legal cases, 74-1375 - 74-1426 (Box 143)
      - Legal cases, 74-1427 - 74-1479 (Box 144)
      - Legal cases, 74-1480 - 74-1547 (Box 145)
      - Legal cases, 74-1548 - 74-1605 (Box 146)
      - Legal cases, 74-1606 - 74-1655 (Box 147)
      - Legal cases, 74-1656 - 74-1689 (Box 148)
      - Legal cases, 74-1690 - 74-1739 (Box 149)
      - Legal cases, 74-1740 - 74-1800 (Box 150)
      - Legal cases, 74-1801 - 74-1851 (Box 151)
      - Legal cases, 74-1852 - 74-1911 (Box 152)
      - Legal cases, 74-1912 - 74-1979 (Box 153)
      - Legal cases, 74-1980 - 74-2039 (Box 154)
      - Legal cases, 74-2040 - 74-2094 (Box 155)
      - Legal cases, 74-2095 - 74-2121 (Box 156)
      - Legal cases, 74-2122 - 74-2174 (Box 157)
      - Legal cases, 74-2175 - 74-2230 (Box 158)
      - Legal cases, 74-2231 - 74-2261 (Box 159)
      - Legal cases, 74-2262 - 74-2304 (Box 160)
      - Legal cases, 74-2305 - 74-2354 (Box 161)
      - Legal cases, 74-2355 - 74-2399 (Box 162)
      - Legal cases, 75-1001 - 75-1050 (Box 163)
      - Legal cases, 75-1051 (-1075, -1088, -1196, and related cases) (Box 164)
      - Legal cases, 75-1052 - 75-1079 (Box 165)
      - Legal cases, 75-1080 - 75-1114 (Box 166)
      - Legal cases, 75-1115 - 75-1159 (Box 167)
      - Legal cases, 75-1160 - 75-1217 (Box 168)
      - Legal cases, 75-1218 - 75-1243 (Box 169)
      - Legal cases, 75-1244 - 75-1281 (Box 170)
      - Legal cases, 75-1282 - 75-1302 (Box 171)
      - Legal cases, 75-1303 - 75-1343 (Box 172)
      - Legal cases, 75-1344 - 75-1400 (Box 173)
      - Legal cases, 75-1401 - 75-1444 (Box 174)
      - Legal cases, 75-1445 - 75-1496 (Box 175)
      - Legal cases, 75-1497 - 75-1514 (Box 176)
      - Legal cases, 75-1515 - 75-1572 (Box 177)
      - Legal cases, 75-1573 - 75-1612 (Box 178)
      - Legal cases, 75-1613 - 75-1649 (Box 179)
      - Legal cases, 75-1650 - 75-1699 (Box 180)
      - Legal cases, 75-1700 - 75-1760 (Box 181)
      - Legal cases, 75-1761 - 75-1801 (Box 182)
      - Legal cases, 75-1802 - 75-1845 (Box 183)
      - Legal cases, 75-1846 - 75-1869 (Box 184)
      - Legal cases, 75-1870/71 only (Box 185)
      - Legal cases, 75-1872 - 75-1910 (Box 186)
      - Legal cases, 75-1911 - 75-1954 (Box 187)
      - Legal cases, 75-1955 - 75-2011 (Box 188)
      - Legal cases, 75-2012 - 75-2044 (Box 189)
      - Legal cases, 75-2045 - 75-2099 (Box 190)
      - Legal cases, 75-2100 - 75-2140 (Box 191)
      - Legal cases, 75-2141 - 75-2182 (Box 192)
      - Legal cases, 75-2183 - 75-2239 (Box 193)
      - Legal cases, 75-2240 - 75-2279 (Box 194)
      - Legal cases, 75-2280 - 75-2314 (Box 195)
      - Legal cases, 75-2315 - 75-2341 (Box 196)
      - Legal cases, 75-2342 - 75-2383 (Box 197)
      - Legal cases, 76-1001 - 76-1059 (Box 198)
      - Legal cases, 76-1060 - 76-1070 (and 76-1168) (Box 199)
      - Legal cases, 76-1071 - 76-1107 (Box 200)
      - Legal cases, 76-1108 - 76-1153 (Box 201)
      - Legal cases, 76-1154 - 76-1189 (Box 202)
      - Legal cases, 76-1190 - 76-1239 (Box 203)
      - Legal cases, 76-1240 - 76-1294 (Box 204)
      - Legal cases, 76-1295 - 76-1349 (Box 205)
      - Legal cases, 76-1350 - 76-1410 (Box 206)
      - Legal cases, 76-1411 - 76-1482 (Box 207)
      - Legal cases, 76-1483 - 76-1490 (Box 208)
      - Legal cases, 76-1493 - 76-1494 (Box 209)
      - Legal cases, 76-1495 - 76-1517 (Box 210)
      - Legal cases, 76-1518 - 76-1539 (Box 211)
      - Legal cases, 76-1540- 76-1609 (Box 212)
      - Legal cases, 76-1610 - 76-1694 (Box 213)
      - Legal cases, 76-1695 - 76-1753 (Box 214)
      - Legal cases, 76-1754 - 76-1801 (Box 215)
      - Legal cases, 76-1802 - 76-1899 (Box 216)
      - Legal cases, 76-1900 - 76-1999 (Box 217)
      - Legal cases, 76-2000 - 76-2109 (Box 218)
      - Legal cases, 76-2110 - 76-2237 (Box 219)
      - Legal cases, 76-2238 - 76-2463 (Box 220)
      - Legal cases, 77-1001 - 77-1206 (Box 221)
      - Legal cases, 77-1207 - 77-1681 (Box 222)
      - Misc. 500 - 989, 1968 Mar. 28-1973 Apr. (Box 223-226)
      - Misc. 72-8002 - 72-8040, 1972 Sept.-1972 Dec. (Box 227)
      - Misc. 73-8003 - 73-8165, 1973 Mar.-1974 Jan. (Box 228)
      - Misc. 74-8002 - 74-8127, 1974 June-1975 Mar. (Box 229-231)
      - Misc. 75-8000 - 75-8447, 1975 May-1976 Aug. (Box 232-235)
      - Misc. 76-8007 - 76-8423, 1975 Dec.-1977 Apr. (Box 236-238)
      - Misc. 77-8008 - 77-8080, 1977 Jan.-1977 May (Box 239)
      - Unnumbered cases, 1966-1977 (Box 240)
    - Circuit Executive, 1974-1977 (Box 241-243)
    - Clerk's Office, 1974-1977 (Box 244-245)
    - Court Administration
      - Agenda and Minutes of Meetings, Judicial Council, 1968-1977 (Box 246)
      - Judicial Council Matters, 1974-1977 (Box 247-249)
    - Court Calendars and Case Notes, 1972-1977 (Box 250-251)
    - Judicial Conferences, 1970-1977 (Box 252)
    - Paper Shuffling File, 1968 (Box 253)
    - Rules, 1966-1975 (Box 253)
  - U.S. District Court
    - Cases:
      - Maryland, 1973-1975 (Box 254)
      - N.C. Western District, 1964-1967
        - Prisoners, Habeas Corpus Cases, 1961-1966 and 1970-1971 (Box 254)
      - N.C. Wilmington District, 1966-1977 (Box 255)
      - Pennsylvania, 1975 (Box 255)
      - Three-Judge, 1965 and 1970-1977 (Box 256-267)